Williamsburgh Savings Bank Building photographs and architectural drawings ARC.116
Brooklyn Historical Society
Williamsburgh Savings Bank Building photographs and architectural drawings
1888-2001
1927-1929
Center for Brooklyn History
Halsey, McCormack & Helmer
Williamsburgh Savings Bank
ARC.116
4.56 Linear Feet in one manuscript box and flat file storage
The Williamsburgh Savings Bank Building photographs and architectural drawings span the years 1888 to 2001, with bulk dates of 1927 to 1929. The collection documents the design, construction, architectural and infrastructural features, and daily work life in the now landmarked building at One Hanson Place in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Fort Greene, particularly between its opening and the early 1960s. The collection is arranged into three series: Photographs, Architectural drawings, and Ephemera.
Historical Note
The Williamsburgh Savings Bank, chartered in 1851, originally opened its doors to customers from a rented basement in the Town of Williamsburgh (now the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn). The bank continued to rent office space until 1875 when the first Williamsburgh Savings Bank building opened at 175 Broadway in what was then the Eastern District of the City of Brooklyn (now, also, the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn). The building, landmarked since 1966, was built following an architectural competition held by the bank to find an architect to design their headquarters. George B. Post submitted the winning design of a four-story Classical Revival style building. Post would go on to design other landmarked buildings including the Brooklyn Historical Society building.
In 1926, the Williamsburgh Savings Bank bought more property, this time in the brownstone adorned Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn. On this site, the 34-story Williamsburgh Savings Bank building, located at 1 Hanson Place, was built. The skyscraper was designed by the architectural firm Halsey, McCormack, and Helmer who specialized in bank architecture. Their designs include the landmarked Emigrant Savings Bank building (originally the Dollar Savings Bank) located in the Bronx.
The Williamsburgh Savings Bank building, 1 Hanson Place was built between 1927 and 1929. Standing at 512 feet, it was the tallest building in Brooklyn until the completion of The Brooklyner condominiums (516 feet) in 2009. The now landmarked Williamsburgh Savings Bank building (since 1977) was also home to the largest four-faced clock in the world. It held this title until 1962. In 2009, the building was converted into condominiums. In 2010, the expansive ornate marbled lobby, originally the banking room, was opened to house the popular weekend market, Brooklyn Flea.
Sources: Allison, Eric Wm. "Williamsburgh Savings Bank." The Encyclopedia of New York City, edited by Kenneth T. Jackson. New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press; New York: New-York Historical Society, 1995. Forgotten NY. Street scenes. Top of the World Ma. http://www.forgotten-ny.com/STREET%20SCENES/willie/willie.html (accessed October 6, 2010).
The Williamsburgh Savings Bank, chartered in 1851, originally opened its doors to customers from a rented basement in the Town of Williamsburgh (now the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn). The bank continued to rent office space until 1875 when the first Williamsburgh Savings Bank building opened at 175 Broadway in what was then the Eastern District of the City of Brooklyn (now, also, the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn). The building, landmarked since 1966, was built following an architectural competition held by the bank to find an architect to design their headquarters. George B. Post submitted the winning design of a four-story Classical Revival style building. Post would go on to design other landmarked buildings including the Brooklyn Historical Society building.
In 1926, the Williamsburgh Savings Bank bought more property, this time in the brownstone adorned Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn. On this site, the 34-story Williamsburgh Savings Bank building, located at 1 Hanson Place, was built. The skyscraper was designed by the architectural firm Halsey, McCormack, and Helmer who specialized in bank architecture. Their designs include the landmarked Emigrant Savings Bank building (originally the Dollar Savings Bank) located in the Bronx.
The Williamsburgh Savings Bank building, 1 Hanson Place was built between 1927 and 1929. Standing at 512 feet, it was the tallest building in Brooklyn until the completion of The Brooklyner condominiums (516 feet) in 2009. The now landmarked Williamsburgh Savings Bank building (since 1977) was also home to the largest four-faced clock in the world. It held this title until 1962. In 2009, the building was converted into condominiums. In 2010, the expansive ornate marbled lobby, originally the banking room, was opened to house the popular weekend market, Brooklyn Flea.
Sources:
Allison, Eric Wm. "Williamsburgh Savings Bank." The Encyclopedia of New York City, edited by Kenneth T. Jackson. New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press; New York: New-York Historical Society, 1995.
Forgotten NY. Street scenes. Top of the World Ma. http://www.forgotten-ny.com/STREET%20SCENES/willie/willie.html (accessed October 6, 2010).
Scope and Contents
The Williamsburgh Savings Bank Building photographs and architectural drawings span the years 1888 to 2001, with bulk dates of 1927 to 1929, and measures 4.5 linear feet. The collection primarily documents to the design and construction of the now landmarked building at One Hanson Place in the neighborhood of Fort Greene, and is organized into three series: Photographs, Architectural drawings, and Ephemera.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Architectural drawings and most photographs gift of HSBC Bank USA in 2006 and 2007. The source of acquisition of photographs in folder 16 is unknown.
Conditions Governing Access
Photographs open to researchers without restriction. Architectural drawings may be restricted due to physical condition. Please consult library staff for more information.
Related Archival Materials
Brooklyn Historical Society also holds a related collection. Interested researchers should see the Williamsburgh Savings Bank records (1990.008). Please consult library staff for more information.
Other Finding Aids
Item-level description and digitized images of photographs from the collection are available for search via the image database in the library and online. There is also a detailed legacy inventory list for the architectural records located in the Othmer Library at Brooklyn Historical Society, completed in 2007. Please consult library staff for more information.
Photograph Records
Item-level description and digital versions of images from the collection are available for searching via the online image database
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Art deco (Architecture); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Buildings, structures, etc.; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Color prints (photographs); Black-and-white prints (photographs); Architectural drawings; Bank buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Holidays |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Design and construction; Drawings (visual works); Color slides; Williamsburgh Savings Bank Building (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.: Hanson Place)
- Series 1: Photographs, 1927-1966; 0.4 Linear Feet (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of black-and-white and color photographic prints documenting the construction, opening, architectural features, employees, and customers of the Williamsburgh Savings Bank Building located at One Hanson Place in the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn. It includes exterior and interior construction photographs, showing the building's foundations, framework, and vault. The series also includes interior photographs of the bank lobby after completion, of holiday installations in the building, and of the vault in use. It also includes images of events held at the building such as the Williamsburgh Savings Bank annual Christmas party, and building tours.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  The photographs in Folders 1 through 15 and all associated rights, including copyright, were transferred to Brooklyn Historical Society in 2008 by Heather L. Nesle, Vice President of Community and Philanthropic Services, HSBC Bank USA, N.A.
  The provenance and source of acquisition of photographs in Folder 16 is unknown. The lack of documentation about them when the bulk of the collection was donated by HSBC Bank in 2006 indicates that they were not part of that accession, but were subsequently added to the collection artificially.
  - Exterior views - construction and early exterior views, 1927-1950; 1927-1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Exterior views - lighting, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Construction - foundations and framework, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Construction - mechanical infrastructure, 1929 February 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Construction - vault, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Construction - lobby, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Tellers and customers, circa 1955-1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bank offices, 1955-1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Vault use, circa 1929-1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tours, circa 1955-1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Holidays, 1946-1966; 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Architectural model, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Drawings, circa 1929-1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Artificial collection, circa 1941-1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    The provenance and source of acquisition of these items are unknown. The lack of documentation about them when the rest of the collection was donated by HSBC Bank in 2006 indicates that they were not part of that accession, but were subsequently added to the collection artificially.
    38 items, showing both the Williamsburgh Savings Bank Building at One Hanson Place and another unidentified bank branch. Materials include black-and-white and color transparencies, black-and-white and color prints, polaroid prints, 3" x 3" and 35mm slides, and two pieces of correspondence that were grouped with photographic materials.
- Series 2: Architectural drawings, 1910-2001; 1927-1929; 4.15 Linear Feet (Flat file folder ARC.116)
  This series consists of approximately 200 architectural drawings and plans for the design and construction of One Hanson Place. The architectural drawings include ground plans, elevations, architectural drawings, technical drawings pertaining to plumbing layouts, mechanical drawings, vault plans, electrical and lighting layouts, and supporting design documents.
  A detailed preliminary inventory of architectural drawings, completed in 2007, is available at Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library.
- Series 3: Ephemera, 1888; 0.1 Linear Feet (Box 1)
  One copy of the Williamsburgh Savings Bank bylaws, dated 1888.